A Guide to the Correspondence and Subject Files of the Virginia Secretary of Transportation, 1976-1978
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Correspondence and Subject Files of the Virginia Secretary of Transportation, 1976-1978
The Library of Virginia
30424
5 cu. ft.
Virginia. Office of the Secretary of Transportation
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was transferred by the Office of the Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety, 6 February 1979.
Biographical Information
The Secretary of Transportation is a member of the Governor's Cabinet, they are selected by the governor, and subject to the approval of the General Assembly. The Secretary is responsible to the governor for the Department of Transportation, Department of Rail and Public Transportation, Department of Aviation, Department of Motor Vehicles, Virginia Port Authority and the Motor Vehicle Dealers Board. Their responsibilities include developing and implementing Virginia's transportation programs, including policies, financial oversight for six agencies and major projects.
In 1972, Governor Linwood Holton proposed to the General Assembly a restructuring of state agencies into six major departments each headed by a secretary to be appointed by the governor. On April 8, 1972 the Department of Transportation and Public Safety was created, by an act passed by the General Assembly. The Office has undergone a series of administrative reorganizations since its creation. On April 12, 1976, the Legislature established separate secretariats for transportation and for public safety, effective July 1, 1976. From July 1, 1984- 1990 the two entities would again be combined under one secretariat. On February 22, 1990 the two were again separated, and have remained so.
The individuals who served as Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety were: Wayne A. Whitham (1976-1978), George M. Walters (1978-1982), Andrew B. Forgarty (1982-1984), John G. Milliken (1990-1993), Robert Martinez (1994-1998), Shirley Ybarra (1998-2002), Whittington W. Clement (2002-2005), Pierce R. Homer (2005-2010), Sean T. Connaughton (2010-1012).
The first Secretary of Transportation (and Public Safety) was, Wayne A. Whitham, a member of the Winchester City Council. Whitham was reappointed by Governor-elect Miles E. Godwin, Jr., in December 1973 and by Governor-elect John N. Dalton in December 1977. Whitham suffered a heart attack in August 1978 and resigned in December 1978.
Scope and Content
Boxes 1-3 consist of records collected by the Governor's Council on Transportation; director Ira F. Doom, and co-chairmen, Senator Paul W. Harris and Secretary Wayne A. Whitham. Types of documents include; agendas, minutes, memorandums, and budgets. There are also files related to financial consultants, studies, rail systems and rural highways. Boxes 4 and 5 consist of budget documents for the individual departments under the direction of the Secretary of Transportation.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence and Subjects Files, 1976-1978., Extent: 5 cu. ft. (5 boxes). (Box 1-5)
  This collection maintains the agency's original filing order, boxes 4-8 are arranged chronologically.
  - Acceptance, Letters of (From members of Council), 1976. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Appointments and Schedules, 1976-1977. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Aviation, Testimony for Deptartment of, 1978. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bills, 1978. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Budget and Expenditures, 1976-1978. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Clean Air Act Projects, 1976-1978. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Commission on State Governmental Management, 1977. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Conflict of Interest, 1977-1978. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Consultants, 1977. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Consultants' Recommendations, 1977. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Council Report, 1976. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Council Meeting, 1977 Nov 14. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Council Report, 1977. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Council, Organization of, 1977. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Grant, Final Report to Urban Mass Transit Administration, undated. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Highway Transportation Research Council, 1977. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Legislative Standing Committee, 1977-1978. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Legislation, Summaries and Fiscal Impact, 1977. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Legislation, 1978. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Office Supplies and Equipment, 1976-1978. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Personnel, 1976-1978. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Ports, 1976-1978. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Port Study Committee, 1977-1978. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Position Papers, 1975-1976. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Revenue Resources and Economic Commission, 1978. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Steering Committee, 1977. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Study Commissions, 1976-1977. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Task Force: Organization and Management, 1978. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Task Force: Urban Transportation Alternatives, 1978. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Taxes, Studies and Research Pertaining to, 1976. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Tidewater Transportation Commission, 1977-1978. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Virginia Port Authority, 1978. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Working Plans: Organization and Management Original, undated. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Working Plans: Northern Virginia, undated. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Working Plans: Eastern Shore Railroad System, undated. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Working Plans: Commonwealth in Role as Employer, undated. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Working Plans: Organization and Management, undated. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Working Plans: Ports, undated. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Working Plans: Role of Governor's Council on transportation, undated. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Air Transportation Subcommittee, 1976. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Energy and Enviroment Subcommittee, 1977. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Highways Subcommittee, 1976. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Minutes: Meetings of State Highway and Transportation Commission, 1976. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Minutes: Northern Virginia Task Force, 1976-1977. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Task Force: Northern Virginia, 1976-1977. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Paratransit Subcommittee (Nothern Virginia Transportation Needs), 1977. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Ports Subcommittee, 1976. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Rail Subcommittee, 1976-1978. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Role Papers, 1977. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Transit Subcommittee, 1976-1977. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Minutes: Urban Transportation Alternative Task Force, 1977. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Urban Transportation Alternatives: Draft Report, 1977. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Urbanized Areas Transportation Organization Subcommittee, 1977. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Budgeting Memorandums: Secretary Rowe, 1976. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Planning and Budget Memorandums, 1972. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Budgeting Memorandums: Governor, 1976. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Budget: House Appropriations, 1975-1977. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Budget: Secretary of Transportation Budget 5 percent Reduction, 1976 Aug 31. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Budget: 2 1/2 percent Reduction Biennium, 1976-1978. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Budget: Expenditure Reduction Impact, 1976-1977; 1977-1978. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - General Fund Revenue Projections, 1975-1976; 1976-1977; 1977-1978. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Budget Act 1974-1975 Six-year Expenditure Plan, 1975. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Budget Act Six-year Expenditure Plan, 1976. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Budget General, 1976-1977. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Budget Related Information, 1975-1977. (Box 4, Folder 12-13)
  - Virginia State Government Program Structure: Planning and Budget, Dept. of, 1975-1977. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - House Appropriations Budget Bill: Highway Revenue Hearing, 1977. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - State Mandated Programs: Senate Finance, 1977 Jan 19. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Package of Budget Memorandums; Draft of Virginia State Government Program Structure, 1975-1977. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Budget: Exhibit - State Police, 1976-1978. (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Budget: 1976 Session Transportation and Public Safety Biennium, 1976-1978. (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Budget: Civil Air Patrol Biennium, 1976-1978. (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Budget: Crime Commisson Biennium, 1976-1978. (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Budget: Criminal Justice Training and Standards Commission Biennium, 1976-1978. (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Budget: Emergency Services Biennium, 1976-1978. (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Budget: Highway Safety Biennium, 1976-1978. (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Budget: Virginia Department of Highways and transportation Biennium, 1976-1978. (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Budget: Central Garage Biennium, 1976-1978. (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Budget: Military Affairs Biennium, 1976-1978. (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Budget: Motor Vehicles Biennium, 1976-1978. (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Budget: Virginia Airport Authority Biennium, 1976-1978. (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Budget: Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority Biennium, 1976-1978. (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Budget: Capital Outlay Biennium, 1976-1978. (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Budget: House Appropriations Committee Biennium, 1976-1978. (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Budget: Transportation and Public Safety Estimates Biennium, 1976-1978. (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Budget: Transportation and Public Safety Presentation Biennium, 1976-1978. (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Six-year Expenditure Plan, 1976. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Six-year Expenditure Plan, 1976. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Tidewater Transportation District Commission Budget Request Biennium, 1974-1976. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - The Budget Bill: House Document 1, 1975. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - House Bill 1100, 1975. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Chapter 464, 1976. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Budget Amendments, 1972-1974. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Transportation and Public Safety: Major Issues, 1975. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Capital Outlay, 1972-1974. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Highway Budget Exhibit, 1972-1974. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Northern Virginia Transportation Commission Financial Report and Five-year Plan, 1976. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Budget: Transportation and Public Safety, 1973. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Budget: Revisions, 1973. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Budget: Military Affairs, 1973. (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Budget: Motor Vehicles, 1973. (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Budget: State Police, 1973. (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Budget: Appropriations Amendments by 1975 General Assembly, 1974-1976. (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Budget: Transportation and Public Safety, 1974-1976. (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Budget: Highway Department, 1974-1976. (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Budget: Short and Long Range Plans for Delegate Ed Lane, 1974. (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Transportation and Public Safety Budget Meeting: Fredericksburg, 1974 June 6-7. (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Port Authority, 1974-1976. (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Budget: Emergency Services, 1974-1976. (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Budget: Highway Safety Division, 1974-1976. (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Budget: State Police, 1974-1976. (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Budget: Law Enforcement Officers Training Standards Commission, 1974-1976. (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Budget: Military Affairs, 1974-1976. (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Budget: Motor Vehicles, 1974-1976. (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Budget: Northern Virginia Transportation District Commission, 1974-1976. (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Budget: Northern Virginia Transportation District Commission (30.88.56), 1974-1976. (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Budget: State Police, 1974-1976. (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Budget: Tidewater Transportation District Commission, 1974-1976. (Box 5, Folder 32)